Nieves Ábalos

+34 699 722 547 nyeves@gmail.com <u>twitter.com/nieves_as</u> Madrid, Spain

Personal web: nieves.abalos.me

Profile

Conversational Interfaces expert. Former Product Manager at BEEVA. Worked with Intelligent Agents and Artificial Intelligence. Research areas: Natural Language Processing, Dialog Systems and Affective Computing and Conversational Interfaces. Computer Engineer and MSc in Software Development.

My goal is to create innovative products to everyday problems powered by technology. Enthusiastic of entrepreneurship and ways of learning sooner the better: Lean Startup, Design Thinking, Rapid Prototyping, etc.

Experience

CONVERSATIONAL INTERFACES EXPERT, BEEVA LABS (A BBVA COMPANY)
MADRID, SPAIN – JUN 2017 - OCT 2017

Research areas: Conversational Interfaces, Voice Interfaces, Natural Language Understanding. Built prototypes with Google Assistant, and benchmarks with Natural Language Understanding tools. More info here http://bit.ly/voice-interfaces and http://bit.ly/voice-interfaces and

PRODUCT MANAGER, BEEVA (A BBVA COMPANY)

MADRID, SPAIN - JUL 2016 - JUN 2017

Product Manager of Clever, a platform to create intelligent software, based on a ecosystem of intelligent agents. It provides Artificial Intelligent services, such as Conversational Interfaces, Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning and Recommender Systems. Product acquired by BBVA.

Team of developers and UX designers. Applying Scrum & Lean Startup methodologies. Professional Scrum Product Owner (PSPO I) certified.

DESIGN LAB LEAD, BEEVA LABS (A BBVA COMPANY)

MADRID, SPAIN - JAN 2016 - SEPT 2016

Product Design, using Design Thinking, Rapid Prototyping, Lean Startup and Agile Methodologies.

Some projects in progress: Chat Bots, Intelligent Agents Platform.

INNOVATION RESEARCHER, BEEVA (A BBVA COMPANY)

MADRID, SPAIN - JAN 2015 - JAN 2016

Research areas: Natural Language Processing, Affective Computing and Natural User Interfaces. Created Unloop (http://beeva-nievesabalos.github.io/nlp-landing/): Natural Language Processing API for Spanish and English.

INNOVATION TECHNICIAN, BEEVA (A BBVA COMPANY) MADRID, SPAIN – APR 2013 - JAN 2015

Research, analysis and development of innovation initiatives in areas: Intelligent agents, Linked Data, Internet of Things (IoT).

Some prototypes and proof of concepts (PoC) made during this period:

- BIKAs (BEEVA Information and Knowledge Assistant) platform: Applied to different domains: meeting room reservations, recruiting and staffing.
- Semantics and Linked Data applied to Big Data.
- API for Natural Language Processing applied to intelligent agents to extract intent from users.
- Email classification, applying Machine Learning.
- Speech recognition (ASR) and text-to-speech (TTS) applications in English and Spanish for Chrome and Android.
- Internet of Things management environment, using different technologies like Bluetooth 4.0, NFC and graphs.

Education

Universidad de Granada, Spain

- PhD in Software Development, Information Technology and Communication, 2011 2013 Evaluation of Spoken Dialog Systems (Not finished)
- MSc in Software Development, 2009 2010 (view thesis)
- Computer Science Engineering, 2003 2009 (view thesis)

Member of the research group "Sistemas de Diálogo Hablado y Multimodal" (SISDIAL) http://sisdial.ugr.es/~nieves_as/datos_personales/ and member of SEPLN (Spanish Society for Natural Language Processing).

Skills

- **Artificial Intelligence**: Human-Computer Interaction, Natural Language Processing, Dialogue Systems, Machine Learning, Knowledge-based systems.
- **Product management, design and development:** Design Thinking, Visual Thinking, User centered design, UX/UI, Product Design, Rapid Prototyping, Lean Startup, Agile (Scrum, Kanban), Professional Scrum Product Owner (PSPO I) and Certified Scrum Product Owner® (CSPO), Social Entrepreneurship.
- **Toolkit**: Git, Linux, Node.js, JavaScript, NoSQL and graph databases (Neo4j), Python and Scikit Learn (Machine Learning library), HTML 5, CSS, Natural Language Toolkit (NLTK), Amazon Web Services (AWS).
- **Past experience**: Google App Engine, Java, Android, iOS, C++, Objective-C, C++, PHP, MySQL, XML, Visual C++, Perl, LaTeX, VoiceXML, Windows Speech Recognition.

Publications

A multimodal dialogue system for an ambient intelligent application in home environments. Springer-Verlag Berlin, Heidelberg 2010. Authors: Nieves Ábalos Serrano, Gonzalo Espejo, Ramón López-Cózar, Zoraida Callejas, David Griol

Design and Implementation of a Toolkit for Evaluation of Spoken Dialogue Systems Designed for Aml Environments. Springer New York 2011. Authors: Nieves Ábalos Serrano, Gonzalo Espejo, Ramón López-Cózar, Zoraida Callejas, David Griol

More publications at: https://goo.gl/n3S6jQ

Talks & Teaching experience

- **Wonder Woman In Tech.** *Inteligencia Artificial* (video). May 2017.
- **UX Academy.** *UX y Diseño de Interacción para Chatbots* (<u>link</u>). April 2017.
- **Fjord Madrid.** From Zero to Hero: Chatbots. April 2017.
- **BEEVA Workshops.** *Natural Language Processing; Chatbots.* 2-day course with theory and practice. 2017 & 2016.
- **BEEVA Meetup.** *UX Design para Chatbots* (video). November 2016.
- Women TechMakers. Mujeres en la innovación (Talk + Workshop). Granada. 2015.